Register of the Sidney Hook papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1917-1990 (Boxes 31-101)
  - "Can We Take Freedom to the Rest of the World?" Town Meeting of the Air radio symposium with Reinhold Niebuhr, Robert A. Taft and Dixon Ryan Fox. Printed transcript, Sept. 23, 1943. (Folder 11)
  - "Faith, Hope, and Dialectic: Merian in Wonderland," Partisan Review, Reply to comments by David Merian on Hook's article "The Politics of Wonderland." Printed copy, and printed copy of Merian's comments, 1943, Sept.-Oct. 1943. (Folder 12)
  - "Illusions of Our Time," Partisan Review, Sept.-Oct. 1943. Review of Harold J. Laski, Reflections on the Revolution of Our Time. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 13)
  - "Charles Beard's Political Testament," Nation, Oct. 23, 1943. Review of Charles A. Beard, The Republic: Conversations on Fundamentals. Typescript, clipping fragment, and letter by Morris R. Cohen (Folder 14)
  - "The Perpetual Debate," Nation, Dec. 11, 1943. Review of Henry Steele Commager, Majority Rule and Minority Rights. Typescript, printed copy, clipping, and letter (Folder 15)
  - "Naturalism and Democracy," in Y. H. Krikorian, ed., Naturalism and the Human Spirit, Printed copy, mimeographed excerpts, and letter, 1944 (Folder 16)
  - "The Rebirth of Political Credulity," New Leader, Printed copy, and letter by J. Miller, 1944, Jan. 1, 1944. (Folder 17)
  - "Humanism and the Labor Movement," New Europe, Printed copy, Feb. 1944. (Folder 18)
  - "Marx and Engels: The Heritage and the Challenge," Lecture, Rand School of Social Science, New York City. Typescript, Feb. 3, 1944. (Folder 19)
  - "God, Geometry and the Good Society," Partisan Review, Spring 1944. Review of Mark Van Doren, Liberal Education. Letter, 1945 (Folder 20)
  - "Thirteen Arrows against Progressive Liberal Education," Humanist, Printed copy, Spring 1944. (Folder 21)
  - "Progressive Liberal Education," Nation, March 11, 1944. Review of Algo D. Henderson, Vitalizing Liberal Education: A Study of the Liberal Arts Program. Printed copy and letters (Folder 22)
  - "Hitlerism: A Non-Metaphysical View," Contemporary Jewish Record, April 1944. Review of Konrad Heiden, Der Fuehrer. Letter (Folder 23)
  - "Ballyhoo at St. John's," New Leader, Two-part article. Printed copies, and correspondence with Scott Buchanan, George S. Counts and others, 1944, May 27-June 3, 1944. (Folder 24)
  - "Is Physical Realism Sufficient?" Journal of Philosophy, Printed copy, Sept. 28, 1944. (Folder 25)
  - "Heroic Vitalism," Nation, Oct. 7, 1944. Review of Eric Russell Bentley, A Century of Hero-Worship. Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Bentley, 1955-1956 (Folder 26)
  - "If Only...," Nation, Oct. 28, 1944. Review of Ludwig von Mises, Omnipotent Government. Printed copy (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - "The Ends of Education," Journal of Educational Sociology, Typescript and letter, 1944, Nov. 1944. (Folder 2)
  - "An Apologist for St. John's College," New Leader, Printed copy, clipping, and correspondence with Alexander Meiklejohn, 1945, Nov. 25, 1944. (Folder 3)
  - "Road to Freedom," New Europe, Dec. 1944. Review of Bronislaw Malinowski, Freedom and Civilization. Printed copy (Folder 4)
  - "Proletariat," in Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1945. Correspondence, 1945-1952 (Folder 5)
  - "The Dilemma of T. S. Eliot," Nation, Typescripts, galleys, printed copy, galleys of a reply by Jacques Maritain, printed comments by others, and correspondence, 1945-1973, Jan. 20, 1945. (Folder 6)
  - "The Degradation of the Word," New Leader, Printed copy, Jan. 27, 1945. (Folder 7)
  - "Man and the Universe of Symbols," Kenyon Review, Spring 1945. Review of Ernst Cassirer, An Essay on Man. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Freedom and Socialism: Reply to Max Eastman," New Leader, Printed copy and letter, 1945, March 3, 1945. (Folder 9)
  - "Democratic Faith and Puritan Piety," Nation, May 26, 1945. Review of Ralph Barton Perry, Puritanism and Democracy. Notes, typescript, galleys, printed copy, and letter (Folder 10)
  - "The Case for Progressive Education," Saturday Evening Post, Typescript, printed copy, clipping, and correspondence, 1945, June 30, 1945. (Folder 11)
  - "A Discussion of the Theory of International Relations," Journal of Philosophy, Contribution to a symposium. Printed copy, Aug. 30, 1945. (Folder 12)
  - "Education for Vocation," Antioch Review, Correspondence, 1945-1946, Sept. 1945. (Folder 13)
  - "Are Naturalists Materialists?" Journal of Philosophy, (co-author with John Dewey and Ernest Nagel). Printed copy, and letters by Harold Taylor and another, 1945-1946, Sept. 13, 1945 (Folder 14)
  - Who Killed Carlo Tresca?(co-author with other members of the Carlo Tresca Memorial Committee). Pamphlet (reissued 1983). Printed copy and letter by Warren Hope, 1982-1983, Oct. 1945 (Folder 15)
  - "The Signs of Aldous Huxley," Saturday Review of Literature, Nov. 3, 1945. Review of Aldous Huxley, The Perennial Philosophy. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "Reflections on the Nuremberg Trial: A Summary Court-Martial for Nazi Criminals," New Leader, Printed copy, Nov. 17, 1945. (Folder 17)
  - "Bertrand Russell among the Sages," Nation, Dec. 1, 1945. Review of Bertrand Russell, A History of Western Philosophy. Typescripts, and correspondence with Melvin Lasky and others, 1945-1951 (Folder 18)
  - Education for Modern Man, 1946
    - General. Promotional flyer, contract, and reviews by John Dewey and others, 1946-1963 (Folder 19)
    - Correspondence with C. J. Ducasse, Felix Kaufmann, Gail Kennedy, Max Lerner, Meyer Schapiro, Milton Steinberg and others, 1946-1974 (Folder 20)
  - "Introduction," in Karl Kautsky, Social Democracy versus Communism, Letter, 1947, 1946. (Folder 21)
  - "Problems of Terminology in Historical Writing," in Theory and Practice in Historical Study: A Report of the Committee on Historiography, 1946 (co-author with Charles A. Beard). Correspondence, 1946-1954 (Folder 22)
  - "The Autonomy of Democratic Faith," American Scholar, Exchange with Raphael Demos. Copyright agreement, printed copy of article by Demos, printed copy of Hook's reply (incomplete), and correspondence with Demos and others, 1945-1979, Jan. 1946. (Folder 23)
  - "Fin du Mondisme: The Birth of a New World Mood in Face of Atombomb," New Leader, Typescripts and printed copy, Jan. 23, 1946. (Folder 24)
  - "Toward Intellectual Teamwork," Commentary, Correspondence with Edgar S. Brightman, Nels F. S. Ferre and others, 1945-1946, Feb. 1946. (Folder 25)
  - "What Is Philosophy?" Nation, March 30, 1946. Review of Brand Blanshard, Curt J. Ducasse, Charles V. Hendel, Arthur E. Murphy and Max C. Otto, Philosophy in American Education: Its Tasks and Opportunities. Printed copy, notes, and letter, 1945 (Folder 26)
  - "Moral Values and/or Religion in Our Schools," Progressive Education, Correspondence, 1954, May 1946. (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Eulogy for Rudolf Kagey, Typescripts and letters, 1946, May 15, 1946. (Folder 2)
  - "The Philosophic Scene: Scientific Method on the Defensive," Commentary, Printed copy and letter, 1946, June 1946. (Folder 3)
  - "Russia's Foreign Policy," New York Times, Letter to the editor relating to comments by Arthur Upham Pope. Typescript and printed copy, Oct. 17, 1946. (Folder 4)
  - "Integrity of Criticism," New York Times, Letter to the editor relating to comments by Arthur Upham Pope on Hook's letter "Russia's Foreign Policy." Printed copy, and printed copy of Pope's comments, 1946, Nov. 2, 1946. (Folder 5)
  - The National Council of Jewish Women on the Present-Day Jewish Scene: A Program Survey of the Organization, Pamphlet. Printed copy, report by the National Council of Jewish Women, and letters, 1946, Dec. 1946. (Folder 6)
  - "Synthesis or Eclecticism?" Philosophy and Phenomelogical Research, Printed copy, and letters by Jerome N. Frank and William H. Kilpatrick, 1947, Dec. 1946. (Folder 7)
  - "Atheism," in Collier's Encyclopedia, Typescript and letter, 1947 (Folder 8)
  - Freedom and Experience: Essays Presented to Horace M. Kallen, 1947 (co-editor with Milton R. Konvitz). Contract, reviews, clipping, and correspondence with T. D. Seymour Bassett, Jacob Billikopf, Milton R. Konvitz, Morton White and others, 1947-1974 (Folder 9)
  - "The Philosophical Basis of American Socialism," Lecture, Princeton University. Outline, and letter by Donald D. Egbert, 1946, Jan. 8, 1947. (Folder 10)
  - "The Plural Sources of Jewish Life in America," Speech, American Jewish Committee conference. Holograph outline, mimeograph, memorandum on conference, and letters by Horace M. Kallen and Joshua Lieberman, 1945-1947, Jan. 25, 1947. (Folder 11)
  - "The Future of Democratic Socialism," Partisan Review, Correspondence with Dorothy Butler Howells, 1947, Jan.-Feb. 1947. (Folder 12)
  - "Philosophy and the Police," Nation, Feb. 15, 1947. Review of John Somerville, Soviet Philosophy: A Study of Theory and Practice. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 13)
  - "Totalitarian Liberalism," Time, Printed copy and letter, 1947, Feb. 17, 1947. (Folder 14)
  - "Intelligence and Evil in Human History: An Answer to Intellectual Defeatism," Commentary, Printed copy and letters, 1947, March 1947. (Folder 15)
  - "What Exactly Do We Mean by Democracy?" New York Times Magazine, Correspondence with Lester Markel, Thomas H. Uzzell and others, 1947-1950, March 16, 1947. (Folder 16)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, (date written). Relates to Henry A. Wallace. Typescript, March 20, 1947 (Folder 17)
  - "First Reflections on 'Ideas for a New Party'," (date written). Typescript and letter to Lewis Corey, 1947, May 1, 1947 (Folder 18)
  - Letter to the editor, Philosophical Review, May 1, 1947 (date written). Relates to review by Henry Merritt Wriston of Hook's book Education for Modern Man. Typescript and galleys (Folder 19)
  - "...And a Response," Nation, Letter to the editor in reply to a letter to the editor by John Somerville relating to Hook's review "Philosophy and the Police." Typescript, printed copy, typescript and printed copies of Somerville's letter, and letters by Somerville and Randall Jarrell, 1947, May 10, 1947. (Folder 20)
  - "Are Carasso's 'Disciplines' Democratic?" Humanist, Printed copy, Summer 1947. (Folder 21)
  - "An Unanswered Letter to the American Jewish Congress," New Leader, Letter to the editor relating to the American Jewish Congress. Printed copy, July 5, 1947. (Folder 22)
  - "Sectarian Education," New York Times, (co-author with others). Letter to the editor relating to the American Council on Education. Letters, 1947, Oct. 1, 1947 (Folder 23)
  - Radio address, WMCA, Reply to a broadcast by J. Raymond Walsh relating to arbitration of a labor dispute regarding the National Council of Jewish Women. Typescripts, printed arbitration decision, typescript of Walsh's broadcast, and correspondence with Walsh and others, 1947, Oct. 16, 1947. (Folder 24)
  - "Mr. Fly's Web of Confusions: An Analysis of a Befuddled Decision," New Leader, Typescripts, galleys, printed copy, clippings, and letters, 1947, Oct. 18, 1947. (Folder 25)
  - "Is the U.S. a Republic or a Democracy?" New York Times Magazine, Correspondence, printed copy of comments by readers, and letters, 1947-1950, Oct. 19, 1947. (Folder 26)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, (date written). Relates to Horace M. Kallen. Holograph and typescript, Oct. 29, 1947 (Folder 27)
  - Interview, Radio broadcast (in German). Mimeographed transcript, Nov. 6, 1947. (Folder 28)
  - "The Source of Value," New York Times, Nov. 16, 1947. Review of Clarence I. Lewis, An Analysis of Knowledge and Valuation. Typescript, printed copy, printed copy of a review of Lewis by Charles A. Baylis, and letter (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - "Mr. Fly Entangles Himself More Deeply," New Leader, Reply to comments by James Lawrence Fly on Hook's article "Mr. Fly's Web of Confusions." Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1947-1952, Nov. 22, 1947. (Folder 2)
  - "Light on a Moot Point," New Leader, Letter to the editor relating to Hook's article "Mr. Fly Entangles Himself More Deeply." Typescript, printed copy, and clipping, 1947, Nov. 29, 1947. (Folder 3)
  - "Some Philosophical Facets of Anglo-American Culture," Speech, Conference on the Heritage of English-Speaking Peoples and Their Responsibility, Sept. 1947. Printed copy and program, 1947, Dec. 1947. (Folder 4)
  - "Does the New Foreign Policy Lead to Peace or War?" Typescript, ca. 1947-1948. (Folder 5)
  - "Do Communists Believe in Force and Violence?" Prospectus and letter, 1948 (Folder 6)
  - "Humanism and the Labor Movement," in Feliks Gross, ed., European Ideologies, 1948. Correspondence with Gross and another, 1948-1949 (Folder 7)
  - "The Meaning of Freedom," Radio address. Typescript, 1948? (Folder 8)
  - "Portrait: John Dewey," American Scholar, Printed copy, and correspondence with Jacob Billikopf, John Dewey and others, 1947-1949, Winter 1948. (Folder 9)
  - "Meeting of Logic and the Arts," New York Times, Jan. 11, 1948. Review of F. S. C. Northrop, The Logic of the Sciences and the Humanities. Typescript, printed copy, and letter, 1949 (Folder 10)
  - "On the Casting Out of Devils," New York Times, Jan. 25, 1948. Review of Sir Norman Angell, The Steep Places. Typescript, printed copy, and letter (Folder 11)
  - "On Historical Understanding," Partisan Review, Typescript and printed copy, Feb. 1948. (Folder 12)
  - "The Communist Manifesto One Hundred Years After," New York Times Magazine, Typescript and correspondence, 1948-1949, Feb. 1, 1948. (Folder 13)
  - "Why Democracy is Better," Commentary, Mimeographed excerpts and correspondence, 1948-1949, March 1948. (Folder 14)
  - "The State: Servile or Free?" New Leader, Printed copy, and correspondence with Milton R. Konvitz and another, 1948-1957, March 13, 1948. (Folder 15)
  - "Academic Freedom," New York Times, Letter to the editor relating to academic freedom in Eastern Europe. Typescript, printed copy, flyer incorporating excerpts from Hook's text, and correspondence, 1948, March 23, 1948. (Folder 16)
  - "The Literature of Disenchantment," New York Times, May 16, 1948. Review of Freda Utley, Lost Illusion. Holograph, typescript, printed copy, and letter (Folder 17)
  - Letter to the editor, American Scholar, Summer 1948. Relates to the American Scholar Forum on American Foreign Policy. Typescript, and correspondence (Folder 18)
  - "Mr. Toynbee's City of God," Partisan Review, June 1948. Review of Arnold J. Toynbee, Civilization on Trial. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 19)
  - "Recommendation," Partisan Review, June 1948. Letter to the editor relating to Jerzy Gliksman, Tell the West. Printed copy (Folder 20)
  - "The Psychology of the Imagination," June 22, 1948. Review of Jean-Paul Sartre, The Psychology of the Imagination. Typescript and letter (Folder 21)
  - Letter to the editor, American Scholar, (date written). Reply to comments by Howard Selsam on Hook's article "Portrait: John Dewey." Typescript and correspondence, 1948, June 23, 1948 (Folder 22)
  - "The Pursuit of Happiness," Life, Letters, 1948-1949, July 12, 1948. (Folder 23)
  - "Drei Grundzge Westlichen Denkens," Monat, Correspondence with Melvin J. Lasky, 1949, Nov. 1948. (Folder 24)
  - "Russia's Slave Labor," New York Times, Typescript and letter, 1948, Nov. 2, 1948. (Folder 25)
  - "New Palestine Party," New York Times, (co-author with others). Letter to the editor relating to the Freedom Party of Israel. Printed copy, clippings, and letter, 1948-1982, Dec. 4, 1948 (Folder 26)
  - John Dewey: Philosopher of Science and Freedom, 1949 (editor). Contract, review, and correspondence with Henry Aiken, George Boas, Herbert Feigl, Lawrence K. Frank, Felix Frankfurter, Horace L. Friess, Horace M. Kallen, Felix Kaufmann, Gail Kennedy, Milton R. Konvitz, Harry Laidler, Edwin W. Patterson, Wilfrid Sellars, Morton White and others, 1949-1971 (Folder 27)
  - "Nature and the Human Spirit," in Proceedings: 10th International Congress of Philosophy, Printed copy and letter, 1948, 1949. (Folder 28)
  - "A Systematic Philosophy, and Testament, by Mr. Russell," New York Times, Jan. 2, 1949. Review of Bertrand Russell, Human Knowledge: Its Scope and Limits. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 29)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, (date written). Relates to Corliss Lamont. Typescript, Jan. 24, 1949 (Folder 30)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, (date written). Relates to a letter to the editor by Henry Pratt Fairchild on education in the Soviet Union. Typescript, printed copy of Fairchild's letter, and letter, 1949, Jan. 26, 1949 (Folder 31)
  - "Communism and the Intellectuals," American Mercury, Printed copy, clipping, and correspondence with James K. McGuire, W. A. Orton, Henry Regnery, Mrs. Raymond Allen Stolle, Freda Utley and others, 1948-1950, Feb. 1949. (Folder 32)
  - "Should Communists Be Permitted to Teach?" New York Times Magazine, Mimeographed and printed copies, typescript and printed copies of comments by Robert K. Carr, Kai Nielsen, Norman Thomas and others, and correspondence with Carr, Jacob Billikopf, W. P. Clark, Will Dennes, C. J. Ducasse, Arthur B. Moehlman, John Nason, Henry M. Pachter, Herbert Solow (with attached memorandum), Ralph D. Tanz, Bernard Weitzman and others, 1949-1956, Feb. 27, 1949. (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - "International Communism," Dartmouth Alumni Magazine, Printed copy, and correspondence with Harold H. Burton, William O. Douglas, Frank Murphy, Wiley Rutledge and others, 1949, March 1949. (Folder 2)
  - "On the Battlefield of Philosophy," Partisan Review, Holograph, typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with Herbert Solow and others, 1948-1949, March 1949. (Folder 3)
  - "The Philosophy of Democracy as a Philosophy of History," Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, Printed copy, and correspondence with Clarence I. Lewis, Paul Arthur Schilpp and others, 1948-1953, March 1949. (Folder 4)
  - "Geneticist's Dismissal Weighed," New York Times, Printed copy, March 7, 1949. (Folder 5)
  - "Freedom and Control in Our Time," Speech, New York University. Holograph, typescript, and mimeograph, March 12, 1949. (Folder 6)
  - Letter to the editor, American Mercury, (date written). Reply to a letter to the editor by James K. McGuire relating to Hook's article "Communism and the Intellectuals." Galleys, and galleys of McGuire's letter, March 18, 1949 (Folder 7)
  - Statement, Relates to the Scientific and Cultural Conference for World Peace, New York City. Typescript, March 20, 1949. (Folder 8)
  - "Academic Freedom and Communism," New York Times Magazine, Mimeograph, letters and comments by others, including mimeographed and printed copies of a reply by Alexander Meiklejohn with attached notes by Hook, 1949-1951, March 27, 1949. (Folder 9)
  - "Science and Freedom," Speech on behalf of Americans for Intellectual Freedom, New York City. Mimeograph and clippings, 1949, March 27, 1949. (Folder 10)
  - "Stand of the Liberals," New York Times, April l3, (with George S. Counts). Letter to the editor relating to comments by Theodore Brameld on Americans for Intellectual Freedom. Typescript, printed copy, printed reply by Brameld, and letter by Alfred Korzybski, 1949 (Folder 11)
  - "The Fellow-Traveler: A Study in Psychology," New York Times Magazine, Typescript, printed copies (in English and in German), and correspondence with Talbot Hamlin, H. E. Hanson and others, 1949-1950, April 17, 1949. (Folder 12)
  - Letter to the editor, Reconstructionist, (date written). Relates to Americans for Intellectual Freedom. Typescript, April 20, 1949 (Folder 13)
  - "Dr. Hook Protests," Nation, Letter to the editor relating to comments by Freda Kirchwey on Americans for Intellectual Freedom. Typescript, printed copy, and printed comments by Kirchwey and others, 1949, April 30, 1949. (Folder 14)
  - "Science, Freedom and Peace," Speech, International Day of Resistance to Dictatorship and War, Paris. Mimeograph, printed copy, and correspondence with Norman Cousins, 1949, April 30, 1949. (Folder 15)
  - "Reflections on the Jewish Question," Partisan Review, May 1949. Review of Jean-Paul Sartre, Anti-Semite and Jew. Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence with William Elton, Len Krasner, and Philip Rahv, 1949-1988 (Folder 16)
  - "A Gallant American Rebel," New York Times, July 17, 1949. Review of Ray Ginger, The Bending Cross: A Biography of Eugene Victor Debs. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "The Literature of Political Disillusionment," American Association of University Professors Bulletin, Correspondence with Ralph E. Himstead and another, 1949-1958, Sept. 1949. (Folder 18)
  - "What Shall We Do about Communist Teachers?" Saturday Evening Post, Printed copy, and correspondence with George E. Axtelle, Ralph H. Lutz, Norman Thomas and others, 1949-1950, Sept. 10, 1949. (Folder 19)
  - "Academic Integrity and Academic Freedom," Commentary, Printed copy, clippings, galleys of comments by another, and correspondence with George E. Axtelle, Charles Baylis, Max Beloff, Elliot E. Cohen, William Dennes, C. J. Ducasse, Thomas Emerson, Horace Friess, Helen M. Lynd, Glenn R. Morrow, Arthur E. Murphy, David Riesman and others, 1949-1974, Oct. 1949. (Folder 20)
  - "How USSR Utilizes Psychological Pressures," Lecture, U.S. Air War College, Maxwell Air Force Base, Ala. Notes, clippings, and letters, 1949, Oct. 6, 1949. (Folder 21)
  - "John Dewey at Ninety: The Man and His Philosophy," New Leader, Printed copy, Oct. 22, 1949. (Folder 22)
  - "Academic Freedoms: Academic Confusions," Journal of Higher Education, Correspondence, 1949, Nov. 1949. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - "Soviet Party Philosophy," New York Times, Letter to the editor relating to Soviet philosophy. Typescript and printed copy, Nov. 18, 1949. (Folder 2)
  - "Professor Hook Replies," Commentary, Letter to the editor in reply to responses by Helen M. Lynd and Arthur E. Murphy relating to Hook's article "Academic Integrity and Academic Freedom." Holograph, typescript, printed copy, typescript and printed copies of letters to the editor by Lynd and Murphy, galleys and printed copy of comments by Irving Howe and another, and correspondence, 1949, Dec. 1949. (Folder 3)
  - "The Place of John Dewey in Modern Thought," in Marvin Farber, ed., Philosophic Thought in France and the United States, 1950. Typescript and correspondence with Farber, 1948-1949 (Folder 4)
  - Review of Herbert Butterfield, Writings on Christianity and History, Holograph (incomplete), 1950. (Folder 5)
  - Review of Leo Huberman, The Truth about Socialism, Typescript and letter, 1950 (Folder 6)
  - "Science and Totalitarianism," Holograph, 1950. (Folder 7)
  - Letter to the editor, Socialist Commentary, Jan. l8, (date written). Relates to communism in China. Typescript, biographical sketch, and correspondence, 1950 (Folder 8)
  - "The Tangled Problems of Democracy," New York Times, Feb. 26, 1950. Review of R. M. MacIver, The Ramparts We Guard. Typescript, biographical sketch, and letter (Folder 9)
  - "Religion and the Intellectuals," Partisan Review, Clipping and correspondence, 1950-1951, March 1950. (Folder 10)
  - "Mr. Hook Replies," Commentary, Reply to letter to the editor by Harold Taylor in response to Hook's letter to the editor relating to Hook's article, "Professor Hook Replies." Holograph, typescript, letter by Elliot Cohen, and typescript copy of Taylor's comments, 1950, March 1950. (Folder 11)
  - "The Scientist in Politics," New York Times Magazine, Reply to George A. Kolstad. Typescript, printed copy, galleys of Kolstad's article, and correspondence with Kolstad, A. J. Muste and others, 1950, April 9, 1950. (Folder 12)
  - "Lenin, oder die Rolle des Einzelnen," Monat, Typescript (in English), and letter, 1949, May 1950. (Folder 13)
  - "Communists in the Colleges," New Leader, Printed copy and clipping, 1950, May 6, 1950. (Folder 14)